Javier Ubillos

Västerås, Västmanland County, Sweden

javier@ubillos.org

+46767647588

linkedin.com/in/javierubillos

Summary

A highly driven and no-ego product and technology leader with broad experience across domains and company sizes

Javier is driven, communicative and strives to always tighten feedbackloops.

Both as a product lead and as a tech lead, one of the most important steps is to connect developers with customers, aiming to engage developers creativity towards solving customer needs.

Experience

Product Development Mentor

IKEA

Mar 2023 - Present (1 year 2 months)

Product Owner & Product Advocate for a cost-effective FLOSS built observability solution directed towards inhouse developers.

Contributing to my own team mostly through stakeholder relations and user-research, but also in any way the team might need to be effective and successful.

Product Development Mentor: Teaching product mindset, lean startup methodologies, iterative delivery and user-interviewing for infrastructure teams and their engineering managers.

Actively driving a observability platform development team in a Product Owner capacity showcasing and teaching the methods to stakeholder management and gaining adoption & traction among users.

Technical Advisor

PeakPaath (previously NudgeLabs) (YC W22)

Jan 2023 - Present (1 year 4 months)

Founder & board member

Clinica Dental Pfister

Jan 2019 - Present (5 years 4 months)

https://www.clinicapfister.cl/

PhD Student

Mälardalen University

2009 - Present (15 years)

PhD Student, computer communications.

"Identity oriented network architectures and mechanisms."

CTO, CPO, Founder

PeakPath

Apr 2021 - Jan 2023 (1 year 10 months)

Founder, CTO & CPO.

Working with "Lean startup" methodologies. Discovering user needs & behaviors through continuous userinterviews, including our developers in the process.

We made it into YCombinator, Winter 2022 batch. Participating in the programme, receiving coaching and participating in demoday.

Bridging the business <-> development gap and setting up an organization where the development team could work directly with stakeholders (often as I, as CTO, was very engaged with customers IT-security compliance).

Together with the founder team; guided the company through product discovery and a pivot, growing our customer base from zero to several hundreds of users.

We built a react-native app, backed by GraphQL, PostgreSQL and Cloud Functions on GCP. Fully "cloud native", ensuring we chose solutions that would minimize operations overhead, letting our developers focus on developing and searching for product-to-market-fit.

DPO responsibilities and responsible for information architecture, security and GDPR compliance for highly sensitive user data (health data).

LOOKLET CTO

Looklet

Jan 2018 - Aug 2021 (3 years 8 months)

CTO with a development team of very diverse skills. Ranging from hardware construction, user application software, server software to photography and retouch skills.

Lead both developers and managers. At its largest time, the full development team consisted of ~30 individuals.

Experience with resizing the team

- Doubled the size of the software developer team (2018-2019) (10 -> 20 ppl) and the unfortunate experience of needing to shrink (2020-2021) shrinking the software developer team (20 -> 10).

We migrated our on-prem, java-only solution towards a cloud-based solution (GCP) and to towards a Java-backend and Typescript/React based frontend (improving CD/Cl ability, recruiting ability and general speed of development).

Transformed the development organization towards autonomous & cross-functional product teams.

Lead development and architecture.

DPO responsibility and GDPR compliance responsibilities.

MaginePro

VP of Engineering, head of product & platform

Magine Pro

Feb 2017 - Dec 2017 (11 months)

Managing the evoution of the Magine distributed media platform.

- Leading a diverse team of ~45 individuals, with responsibilities ranging from mobile clients and consoles to pure-backend and infrastructure and teams.
- Aligning diverse teams towards delivering end-to-end value.
- Balancing development of business strategic capabilities and tactical shorter term development to meet our customers needs.

Day-to-day operations include the full range from negotiating and setting strategic goals together with business partners and stakeholders to personally operationally leading development teams (awaiting hiring the right lead-hire) to mentoring/coaching my team of product owners and managers.



Engineering Manager

Magine Pro

Jul 2016 - Feb 2017 (8 months)

- Line manager responsibility as well as product owner responsibility for the payments and subscription cross functional team and the meta-data systems engineering team.
- Mentoring our customers implementation teams leadership.
- Interim line manager for testers
- Product owning our SmartTV and console development team.
- Mentoring of emerging leaders within our organization.
- Continously improve coordination and communication within Magine through coaching and empowering.
- Contributing to magine in a wide variety of ways, filling in whichever role is needed. Ranging from recruiting coordination, patent incentive processes, research collaborations to coordination of internal projects and delivery dependencies.



Product Owner

Magine Pro

Dec 2014 - Jul 2016 (1 year 8 months)

- Product owning the direct-to-consumer web team, delivering several new features to our users.
- Starting Magines first dedicated cross-functional team (chartered to improve retention and activation KPIs, making Magine a personalizable experience).
- Product owning TV-guide integrations between Magine and partners.
- Product owning Magines meta-data infrastructure team.



Technical Product owner - Operational Monitoring

Spotify

Jun 2013 - Dec 2014 (1 year 7 months)

As a product owner for the monitoring team at Spotify, we are engaged in providing insights and tooling to manage the Spotify backend (>10k servers, both bare-metal and virtual).

We are engaged in the Spotify efforts to create truly autonomous teams, where a team might have limited or no experience in operating the services they create. To serve these teams, we focus on

easy-to-use tools for operational insight, ranging from real-time on-call scenarios to long-term capacity planning.

Here's a selection of what we created that was later openly shared:

A high resolution Time Series DataBase we created: https://github.com/spotify/heroic (back then, the backend was Cassandra, whereas today it's BigTable)

A metrics forwarder (we created to be more efficient than collectd): https://github.com/spotify/ffwd

Founder

MSL Technologies AB

Aug 2011 - Oct 2013 (2 years 3 months)

Custom PCB production, at the quality, price and speed-of-delivery that best fits you!

In this startup, we attempted to differentiate by keeping a tighter loop between the PCB-producers and the customers. At this time, the competition where trying to capture the customers by filtering all communication between the PCB-producers and the customers, leading to slower communication loops, more iterations and more mis-productions, all resulting in longer leadtimes and a more expensive chain.

We produced PCB to spec for a wide range of possible standards and customer requirements, in any of our partner factories in the nordic, E.U, outside of E.U and in Asia.



Technical Product Owner - Data Collection

Spotify

Jun 2012 - Jul 2013 (1 year 2 months)

The data collection team where chartered with providing self-serve solutions for data collection and A/Btesting. Both for real-time use as for batched consumption (e.g. billing or A/B-test analysis).

We improved the existing monitoring infrastructure in parallel with creating a reliable real-time logging pipeline (based on Apache Kafka (0.7), which we used to create a 100% delivery guarantee or halt pipe-line). The data was used for anything between labels-reporting and debugging of the Spotify client to A/B testing the performance of the Spotify client.



Backend Infrastructure Developer

Spotify

Oct 2011 - Jun 2012 (9 months)



Project Manager & Lead Developer in Computer Communications research area.

RISE Research Institutes of Sweden

Feb 2007 - Oct 2011 (4 years 9 months)

Leading the development of name-based sockets in collaboration with Tsinghua University, Ericsson Research (San Jose) and master students (Royal Institute of Technology, Mälardalen University).

Research Engineer

ABB Corporate Research

Education

Υ

Y Combinator

Jan 2022 - Apr 2022

Mälardalen University

Master of Science, Computer Science 2002 - 2008

Mälardalen University

Master of Science (M.Sc.), Computer Si

Skills

Organizational Development • Java • Google Cloud Platform (GCP) • Management • Agile Project Management • Product Management • Team Leadership • Group Dynamics • Distributed Systems • Software Engineering

Honors & Awards

Technical Program Committee - SNCNW

Apr 2014

Academic reviewer for the TPC of SNCNW 2014

Academic reviewer - Elsevier

Jul 2011

Reviewed academic papers for Elsevier.

Technical Program Committee - SNCNW

Apr 2015

Academic reviewer for the TPC of SNCNW 2015

Technical Program Committee - SNCNW

Apr 2016

Academic reviewer for the TCP of SNCNW 2016

Technical Program Committee - SNCNW

Apr 2017

Academic reviewer for the TCP of SNCNW 2017